We are on page 18 in the booklet. Okay, so the next sugya that we are going to learn which will take us a few weeks is the topic of stam yeinam. Okay, so we know that we'll just start. If you look at source number one, okay, we'll just get right into it. A lot of very relevant things we're going to talk about: non-Jewish housekeepers and maids and cleaning services that might touch your wine, non-religious people, gifts, things like that.
So the pasuk tells us in Sefer Devarim, the pasuk says: פסילי אלוהיהם תשרפון באש. Okay, you're supposed to, you gotta burn and destroy all avoda zara. לא תחמוד כסף וזהב עליהם. Right, so you can't benefit or get any use out of things that were done for avoda zara. Okay, that is clear. The Gemara in Avoda Zara in source number two, the Gemara tells us: yayin minalan. So, not only is... so where do we know this? אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
קרא אשר חלב זבחימו יאכלו ישתו יין נסיכם. מה זבח אסור בהנאה, just like something that was really done for avoda zara is assur behana'ah, אף יין נמי אסור בהנאה. So too there is an issur d'oraisa from benefiting from wine that was used as for, now there's a term called, which we're going to learn about, yayin nesech. So what's yayin nesech? What was that used for?
For libations. For real avoda zara. So the Gemara says if there was wine used for avoda zara, and you took that wine and you cooked with it or you drank it or you benefited from it, that would be an issur d'oraisa. Okay. Now this is what's called yayin nesech. Okay, this is what's called yayin nesech. The Rambam in source number three, the Rambam says the following: yayin sheninsach l'akum, wine that was really used for avoda zara is assur behaniya. You cannot benefit from it. והשותה ממנו
כל שהוא and as long as you drank even a little bit. Malkot? לוקה מן התורה. Okay, you get malkos for benefiting or drinking even a small amount of this. The Rambam in source number and halacha beis: יין שננסך כזבח שקרב לו וכיון שאיסור זה משום עכו\"ם ein lo shiur. There is no amount that one would be... sometimes there's a kezayis
and a kabeitza. The end of the day, one is not able... this is very clear. This is yayin nesech. So if there was... now we're going to see later there really isn't avoda zara anymore. We don't have people that are using wine for avoda zara. A Christian coworker has a bottle of wine at his house, he's not using that for libations, okay? If he is, it's very strange, it doesn't really have that happening anymore. So now what do we do with that? Okay, but that's yayin nesech. That's topic number one: yayin nesech, wine used for
actual avoda zara purposes. If you use that wine, you drink that wine, you benefit from that wine, assur d'oraisa and you get malkos. Fine. Now, the Gemara in Avoda Zara says: What happens if the wine just belongs to the non-Jew? Meaning he's not there sitting there and pouring it out for avoda zara purposes, but he owns it. So the Gemara in Avoda Zara in source number four says the following: אתא רב אחא בר אדא אמר רבי יצחק גזרו על פיתן
משום שמנן. So they gozer there... there's a number of things that we do to prevent intermarriage, okay? What are those things? So we have... what are those things? Their bread. We have pas akum. Okay, we have bishul akum. And we have wine. So the Gemara says we are gozer on their bread because of the oil. מאי אלמיה דשמנא מפת אלא על פיתן ושמנן
משום יינן. Because of the wine. And the Gemara says in Avoda Zara, the idea sometimes in Chazal of like a slippery slope is a real thing. So the Gemara says: Why am I really worried about wine? I'm worried about wine because what might happen? ועל יינם משום בנותיהם. So what's going to happen? Wine owned by a non-Jew, not avoda zara wine, not avoda zara wine, but wine owned by a non-Jew which what do we call in halacha? That's called stam yeinam.
Stam yeinam means it's not wine that was really done for avoda zara purposes, but it's wine that's owned by a non-Jew. That wine, says the Gemara, is assur. Mishum bnoteihem because we are concerned that it might come to mix together. Now, one more Mishnah, just as background. Okay, so it seems though that maybe this should be... only I can't drink it. I won't drink your wine.
The Gemara says in Avodah Zarah in source number five, אלו דברים שעובדי כוכבים אסורין. What are the things of a guy that are assur and issurei issurei hana'ah? But also are benefited from. One of those is wine. וחומץ של עובדי כוכבים שמתחילתו יין. So what is very clear from these few first sources, for those that just joined us, we read through five quick sources. There is an very straight issur in the Torah, you
cannot benefit from something that is done for avodah zarah purposes. So if some guy gives you a bottle of wine and said I just used half this bottle of Moscato for avodah zarah purposes and you drink the rest of that bottle, that's an issur d'oraissa. That's number one. The Gemara says and that's the Rambam says is even if you drank a little bit, assur mi'doraissa, you get makkos. The Gemara in Avodah Zarah in source number four, number five says even stam yeinam, was not used for avodah zarah, that is also assur because of a gezeira you might come to mix with
people together. Not for hana'ah, right? One second, hold on. So the, if it's no, that's the, the Gemara just said that. You cannot benefit from it. Issurei issurei hana'ah. So why did I get a psak that someone, Rabbi Doug, Rabbi Doug. You joined this shiur forty-two seconds ago. We are starting four weeks of stam yeinam. So we're going to learn through the marei mekomos and then we're going to get to your psak. What, what is the
psak? So the psak was if someone gave you a bottle of non-kosher wine, you could give it to somebody else. We didn't get to that yet. Give me a minute. We're going to get there. We're not actually going to get there. Oh we are going to get there. Okay. So there's three things. There's stam yeinam, I'm sorry, there's yayin nesech, that's assur mi'doraissa. There's stam yeinam that is ordinary non-like non-avodah zarah wine owned by a non-Jew, that is assur for drinking and for benefit. And then there
is Jewish owned wine which we haven't really talked about yet. Okay. Now, if we go to source number six, so why would Chazal forbid us from stam yeinam? I understand yayin nesech, that's used for avodah zarah. Why can't I benefit from stam yeinam? So there is a very, very important machlokes here, the three-way machlokes about the the root of why it's assur. So let's begin in the Beit Yosef. Okay, very, very important three-way
machlokes. So the Beit Yosef says the following, quoting first the Piskei Rid and the Beit Yosef himself, Peirush, אע\"פ שבשאר דברים שגזרו עליהם, there are three things: bishul akum, pas akum, and stam yeinam. The other things like pithan v'shamnam, like their bread and their oil, and certain things like that, לא אסרו אלא באכילה, v'lo b'hana'ah. If somebody gives you, if a guy gives you,
we're meikel today on pas palter. Okay, sorry, on pas akum. We're meikel on pas akum, right? All of us that don't eat pas yisrael, maybe some of you that are makpid on it, but those of us that don't, it's a big kula, but we rely on it. We rely on it. So but if a guy came over to you and said, listen, I have this unbelievable bread, it's kosher with but I baked it, you could use that to fuel your, I don't know, your what? Feed the dog, right, whatever you want, you can
benefit from it. We wouldn't be upset about it. Same is true, but why is it when it comes to the wine, I don't know if dogs drink wine or not, probably we don't know. Right, but if I gave you the bottle of wine, that that would be a problem. So why, so the Beit Yosef asks, why are we more machmir on wine than everything else? ובסתם יינם גזרו לא אסרו אף בהנאה. Here we're more machmir. V'hata'am, and he explains, משום דכיון דיין נסך אסור בהנאה מדאורייתא. Because here
and this is a very, very important rule in halacha, there is already a context that exists. When it comes to pas akum, when it comes to bishul akum, there isn't a context that exists in the Torah mi'doraissa. Here there is a mi'doraissa concept, you cannot benefit from a wine that was used in avodah zarah, it's called yayin nesech. So if I'm basing my things off of that, so says the Beit Yosef, כשבאו חכמים לגזור על סתם יינם,
when the chachamim are going to come and now be gozer and make certain decrees, שכאילו נתנסך וודאי ממילא הוא אסור בהנאה. So if I am Chazal, bread and oil, they have no comparison in the d'oraissa level. Okay, so they only gozer you can't eat from them, but you could benefit from them. But I have But I have a concept in the Torah and I have a concept in Halacha called yayin nesech. So if I'm going to base my d'Rabanan on my d'Oraisa,
I'm going to base it on the same thing and I'm going to make this asur even on a d'Oraisa, I'm sorry, on a d'Rabanan level but still benefiting from hana'ah. That's Beis Yosef. Then he quotes the Ran. v'haRan kasav sham. So the Ran says hold on. כי אם בשתייה היו אוסרים סבורים לומר שמשום ניסוך נאסר because what might happen if they forbade stam yeinam out of
a concern they might be confused ויבואו להתיר יין נסך ואפילו בהנאה. They're not going to know what wine. Wine looks like wine. What you're going to see in the next few weeks, I'm not a wine person, but the really great wines and the really cheap wines and the really medium wines they all look like wine. So I don't know what wine you're drinking. I don't know that that's yayin nesech versus stam yeinam. I have no idea. So I might think they're all mutar. They're all allowed. So therefore Chazal extended the thing and said we don't want anybody to make an assumption
that yayin nesech is mutar be'hana'ah. So Chazal said it's just easier. It's easier sometimes to just make what we call a lo plug. It's too confusing. It's too confusing. You're going to drink. I'm going to ask you every time was that yayin nesech? Was that stam yeinam? You can't benefit from any wine that is owned by a goy. They might mix it anyway so you wouldn't know the difference. Correct, they might mix it anyway. It's easier. Stay away. It's not like the Beis Yosef. The Beis Yosef has its roots in a d'Oraisa but that's the, that is the Ran. Okay, that's the Ran. So that's the Beis Yosef and
that's the Ran. In comes the Rashba in source number seven. Says the Rashba אבל הרשבא כתב בתורת הבית שגזרו על סתם יינם משום בנותיהם לא אסרוה אלא בשתייה. One second, says the Rashba. What's the reason? yayin nesech I get. avodah zarah I can't benefit it. The pasuk says פסילי אלוהיהם תשרפון
באש. Fine. If a goy owns a bottle of wine and that wine is not used for avodah zarah what's the reason I can't drink his wine? What did the Gemorah say? Because of intermarriage. Okay. So then what should be asur? Drinking the wine. So that, the Rashba says that is. This is a fascinating Rashba because sometimes you have to understand the progression of Halacha. The Beis Yosef and the Ran. The Beis Yosef says no, no, no. The d'Oraisa is here. So even though the d'Rabanan is lower level
because it can't be on a d'Oraisa, it is patterned after the d'Oraisa and if the d'Oraisa is asur be'hana'ah, the d'Rabanan is asur be'hana'ah. Fine. The Ran says no, no, no. Really it's just drinking but people are going to just benefit for yayin nesech but because we're going to get confused we made them parallel. The Rashba says no, no, no. Here's the progression. When Chazal came in they said intermarriage, we're very worried. Therefore stay away from drinking. We're not going to sit at a bar together if I'm
just holding your bottle of wine. We're not going to mingle too much. So therefore the Rashba, but then the Rashba, right. But that's just it. Wouldn't I think that the drinking also, my first thought would be drinking with you as well. Hold on, give me a second. שגזרו על סתם יינם משום בנותיהם לא אסרוה אלא בשתייה. Okay. Now, v'Beis Din she'lachareihem. Okay, to Shai's point you're right. Later, so it's a fascinating Rashba. Later, okay, however by the time of the Gemorah ראו שהורגלו הרבה לנסך.
They saw that people were actually getting lax with yayin nesech. ולפיכך הוסיפו באיסור היין. So they decided we're going to now make a decree to say וגזרו על סתם יינם שאסור בהנאה. This is very indicative. There is a Rashba when it comes, I think we might have covered this Rashba. There's an opinion of the Rashba when it comes to Taharas Hamishpacha when it comes to harchakos. So the Rambam very famously holds all harchakos are d'Oraisa.
Most Rishonim don't hold like that Rambam. The Rashba says that really like negi'ah is asur because it might lead. So the Rashba is saying you're right. Really it's just drinking because that's the decree. However, similar issue to the Ran, we saw what was happening. So Chazal, everything is asur. Everything is asur. We don't want you getting mixed up with yayin nesech and therefore everything is going to be asur. So according to the Beis Yosef, Chazal gave the status of
stam yeinam like yayin nesech. That's the Beis Yosef at the top. According to the Ran, really it was to prevent intermarriage but it's getting confusing to know which one so they said it's asur to both. And the Rashba really agrees with the Ran but understands a little bit the progression a little bit differently. Okay. What's the difference between the Ran? Not much. Not much. Just for context. According to the—yeah. According to the—the only difference is, there's not a difference in practice. The only difference is that according to the Rashba it was stage one and stage two, and according to the Ran it was stage one.
There was never a stage two, but that's how the Rashba understands it. Fine. Now. So, how do we pasken, you know, why was this, you know, made this decree? So if you look now in the מדרש פרקי דרבי אליעזר. So on the one hand, you find the following source. After the story of the episode with the women of Midian, in the end, Balak and Parshas Pinchas, אלעזר המודעי אומר עמד פנחס והחרים על ישראל. So, you know, after all of this terrible, Bilaam
tries to curse the Jews and it doesn't work. Eventually gets them to be seduced by the women of Midian. So the—afterwards, after Pinchas gets up, after all the Jews had illicit relationships that they should not have had, culminating in Cozbi and Zimri, so Pinchas enacts a specific decree when it comes to wine. Ubesod Shem Hamiforesh he makes a decree in the name of God עם הקדוש ברוך הוא בכתב שנכתב על הלוחות ובחרם בית דין העליון ובחרם בית דין התחתון. He says makes a
decree שלא ישתה אדם ישראל מיינם של גוים kemarpish raglam. This is very very very bad and therefore we need to stay far away from this. So Pinchas makes a decree that we are staying, you know, as far away from stam yeinam as possible. So there was interesting timelines as to when exactly this whole decree happened, but if you look in the Ramban, the Ramban says there are contradictory sources, like pesukim in Daniel that made it seem as though it was already applicable at the time of Daniel, maybe later than Pinchas, so says the Ramban.
The Ramban says וכיון דתניא פרק דרבי אליעזר הגדול שאליהו גזר על היין ועל דבר פעור. Ve'ika lemeimar, gazar ihu shtiya, Pinchas really decreed you cannot drink it, ואתו אינהו גזרו אפילו בהנאה. And later they came and they were gozer on all the other things. Or he says, לא פשט תקנו אליהו
ודניאל חוזר והורה עליו. Either way, there's a little bit of a debate as to when exactly this whole decree happened, but nonetheless this is the decree, we do not benefit from stam yeinam. Okay. If you have those little packets right here, if you need one they're on the table, this is the Shulchan Aruch. We just need a little bit for tonight. So, if you look in the Shulchan Aruch in Kuf-Chaf-Gimmel, Se'if Aleph. Kuf-Chaf-Gimmel, Se'if Aleph.
Says the Shulchan Aruch. סתם יינם של עמים עובדי כוכבים אסור בהנאה. You cannot benefit from the wine no matter what. והוא הדין במגע ביין שלנו, and similarly if it was touched, they touched our wine which we'll get to in a minute. I know it's hard to see this Rama, but the Rama adds the following. The Rama says,
משום גזירת יין שנתנסך לאלילים, the Rama adds this was, you know, we were concerned about benefiting from yayin nesech. Now, he goes on to say, we'll come back to this in a second, בזמן הזה שאינו שכיח שאומות מנסכין לעבודת כוכבים, alright we'll come back to this, you know, even today, lema'aseh it does not seem like there's—what—once Chazal eliminated the the the avoda
zara as the Gemara says, shouldn't this become not as big a concern and we have to have chumra on top of chumra on top of chumra? So, yes and no. Meaning there might not be a drive for avoda zara but there are certain things that still qualify as avoda zara. I mean, we don't have avoda zara like it was in the times of Mitzrayim and the times of the Gemara, but we do have avoda zara that exists today. We do have people that are, I mean you if you consider like the major major machlokes, Ran and all the Rishonim whether or not you consider Christianity avoda
zara. So most do. I mean, most will consider Christianity avoda zara, maybe not avoda zara like paganism, there's not as much paganism, but it might be avoda zara. איסלם אינמי עבודה זרה. But you're right. On the other hand also, once you have a gezeira, you know, a Beis Din cannot be mafkia, you can't just say this doesn't apply anymore. So once you have a decree in place, you have a decree. On top of the fact that there is
an intermarriage concern which which clearly we have a problem about. Right? So that would still apply. I mean the de-rabbanan of stam yeinam would still apply. So we'll talk about that. We'll talk about that. Okay. So now, so but you go to the Shulchan Aruch... Wait for a second and let's go to now source number ten. Okay? Source number ten. So if I cannot benefit from stam yeinam, so what do I do? Can I give a non-kosher
wine to somebody else? If I was gifted a non-kosher bottle of wine, like Rabbi Doug is saying, could I re-gift it to somebody else? Okay? So we said obviously you can't drink stam yeinam and we saw the different rishonim. So now let's see the Tur in source number ten. So the Tur quotes the Rashbam in certain ge'onim ורשב''ם כתב בשם רש''י שכתב להשיב להגאונים דבזמן הזה אין איסור הנאה במגע של
גוי ביין שלנו that we are meikel, there is no issur hana'ah of wine that was touched by a goy, that you can benefit from wine owned by a non-Jew. Okay? Why? To Shaya's point דגויים בזמן הזה אינן רגילים לנסך לעבודה זרה והוה ליה אינן איסה כי לא אינם יודעים מטיב עבודה זרה ומשמשו והוה כתינוק שעושה יין נסך לאסור בשתייה ולא בהנאה. So
Rashi says you can for sure benefit from wine that was owned by a non-Jew. How do I know that? Because Chazal never said if you have a non-Jewish neighbor and a little the one day the two-year-old comes over to gift you a bottle of wine. Okay? We're going to say oh my gosh. First of all, there's a lot of other problems. Okay? But etzem the fact that he was someone managed to hold a bottle and it didn't break, okay?
You'd be like, wow, that's an amazing baby. Okay? After you got over that whole scenario, that's not assur. Why is that not assur? Because a two-year-old baby is not worshipping avodah zarah. You're also not having relations. Right, right. So therefore, the Gemara was clear about that. Since there's no concern that this kid was going to offer this wine as nisuch, therefore it should so therefore since today's goyim are mostly are not all of them are not pouring this wine. Yes, if you lived in India
and you lived right next to some Buddhist temple, I probably would tell you shouldn't benefit shouldn't touch any of their wines. But other than that you're... I'm just wondering though, the church, if they use wine... Oh, okay, okay. In hach nami, if it's avodah zarah. In hach nami, but but... We just said it's avodah zarah. No no no. You said some opinion. One second. One second. One second. One second. One second. There's a lot of ways to answer your question. First,
you'd have to even just that, you'd have to answer if that was considered nisuch or not. Meaning let's assume after mass the priest comes over to your house and gives you this half a bottle. Meaning was that what they did was was avodah zarah or was it like Kiddush at service? I don't know. Okay? That's number one. Number two, granted that happens, but רוב ורובא דרובא דרובא the non-Jew at your at work who says Happy Hanukkah that you he
gives you wine or you give him wine, we're not worried that that was used in his house for avodah zarah. It's also a closed bottle usually. We're going to talk about that. But you're right, you're right, you're right. Yeah. So that's Rashi. That's Rashi. So therefore lemayseh today, since non-Jews don't really perform nisuch or libations, they're the same thing as this baby and therefore you could benefit from that wine. You cannot
drink that wine, but you could benefit from that wine. That means I could take the wine and I could give it as a gift. Okay. Fine. That is the opinion of Rashi. If you look in source number eleven, then the Tur quotes the Rosh and the Rosh is a little bit more, you know, a little bit more restrictive. Va'adoni avi ha'Rosh. So the Rosh says the following.
ואדוני אבי הרא''ש שהאריך בזה בסוף דבריו ודחא כל המביאים להתיר מגע גוי ביין שלנו אבל סתם יינם שחמור משום בנותיהם אין טעם להתירא. Meaning to your point, the Rosh says, \"How do I know that this isn't the bottle from church?\" You want to tell me that he came over to my house and touched my bottle of Moscato? Fine. Nicha. That's fine. He's not
doing anything wrong. But how do I know that the bottle that came from his house he didn't do anything with? And therefore, don't come... don't come to me with with that the bottle was closed or not—hold on a second. Okay, so that is what the Rosh says, ein tam l'atirah. Now, ומיהו יש לומר שמתחילה לא נאסרו סתם יינם אלא בשתייה. In the beginning, like the Rashba said before, it was only assur with drinking, dapas shemen v'shelakos, אלא משנתרגלו לנסך but when they started to use these also for avodah zarah, אסורה
בהנאה כיין שעשה עבודה זרה. V'innah, so the Rosh says today, שאין מנסכין דין שנעשה סתם יינם כפת ושלוקות. Really, really says the Rosh that we should make it like everything else. מכל מקום ראיה ברורה אין לנו להתירה בהנאה והנח להם לישראל מוטב שיהיו שוגגין ואל יהיו מזידין. Really says the Rosh, we really really shouldn't do this. We really should only benefit from wine that is our wine touched by a goy. But their wine, that
should not be meikel on, so the only scenario we're allowed benefit is a non-Jew touched the Jewish wine. Much more restrictive than the opinion of Rashi. Does it matter if it's open or closed? We're going to talk about that. If it's closed? We'll talk about that, we're going to talk about that in a little bit, we're going to talk about that in a little bit. Yeah, and when we come to how all these kind of issues when with stam yaynam and yayin nesech and things like that, which are major problems, they could treif up your kitchen more than we realize if you use...
Okay, fine. So now, that's the Rosh. If you look at the Rambam, so the Rosh basically ends that he's not compelled enough to allow it and therefore is pretty machmir. The Rambam in source number twelve, the Rambam as understood by the Beis Yosef, שדעת הרמב\"ם שלא לחלק. The Rambam says doesn't matter, doesn't even today, בין גויים שבזמנם לגויים שבזמננו. Doesn't matter, it is forbidden says the Rambam to benefit from stam yaynam or Jewish
wine touched by a non-Jew. Okay? So even though they don't perform any kind of nisuch today, there is no distinction and therefore you have the Rashi who's the most lenient, source number ten, that's Rashi. Then you have the Rosh that's a little bit more lenient, a little less lenient, that they can touch our wine but we cannot benefit from their wine. And the Rambam that says everything should be assur b'hana'ah. Okay. So how do we pasken? So now go back to the
Shulchan Aruch. So we just saw that the Shulchan Aruch paskened like the... one out of three chance... like the Rambam. Like the Rambam. Eddie you got one point. סתם יינם של עובדי כוכבים אסור בהנאה והוא הדין למגעם ביין שלנו. Like the Rambam, like the Rambam. Okay, now the Rema says the
following: משום גזירת יין שנסתייך לעלילים. We're worried maybe they're using it for avodah zarah. ובזמן הזה שאינו שכיח שאומות מנסכים לעבודת כוכבים. Today it is not so common that the goyim are using this for real avodah zarah purposes. יש אומרים דמגע עובד כוכבים ביין שלנו, like the Rosh, if they
do touch our wine, eino assur b'hana'ah. It is not assur b'hana'ah, rak b'shtiyah. וכן בסתם יינם שלהם, their wine, אינו אסור ליהנות ממנו. We really shouldn't benefit from. ולכן מותר לגבות חובו מעובד כוכבים סתם יינם. So therefore if the only thing he could pay back his loan with is with a bottle of his wine then we are going to allow it. And that
really is how the Rema paskens. That although some are buying and selling stam yaynam, you really really should be machmir, but we will be meikel in the case of hefsed. It's very important to understand whenever we have a halacha like this and this is why Smichas Chaver is amazing, the Rema is not being like, listen, halacha is X, but if there's a financial concern we could be lenient. You can only be lenient if there's a reason, if there's a context in halacha to be lenient. So the Rema says we really pasken, the Beis Yosef, the Shulchan Aruch paskens like the Rambam.
We have the Rosh. So says the Rema, we should be machmir about it. But because the Rosh's opinion exists in case of financial issue you can rely on the Rosh. You can rely on the Rosh. You could hear, listen, I can't pay back but I could pay you back with a bottle of wine. Okay, so you pay back with a bottle of wine because we're not really concerned he's using it for avodah zarah. But it's not something that we should become accustomed to because if we become accustomed to it it's going to be an issue. Yes. So if it's a what if wait. Wait till we get to all the practical examples. If it's a what if,
wait till we get to all the practical examples. If it's a can you, wait till we get to the examples. Can you sell wine to a non-Jew that might use it for Avodah Zarah? Well, you can't, no way! If the guy, if the guy says yeah, listen, I'm short of wine for my nisuch purposes, then yes, that would be assur. The same reason you cannot give, you cannot give a Christmas present, right? The Gemara in Avodah Zarah is very clear that within the few days right around their Yamim Tovim you can't give things.
Today we're a little more lenient about it and you shouldn't say this is a Christmas gift. You can say it's an end-of-year bonus, holiday gift. But if you have a staunch, you know, if you're about to give this guy a bottle of wine and he's like \"oh yes, we need it for church\", you would not be able, you'd have to take it right back. 100%. That would be assur. 100% would be assur. Yeah. Yeah. I told you that story once, no? With the Israeli guy on Erev Pesach? A number of years ago there was a, I was at my in-laws, this was before I was even a rabbi because I was, you know, I had
off-Pesach. How many is he up to? A lot. What? Those were the days. You can take it. What? We're not taking your blood pressure, Daddy. I just going to take the medicine up at the moment. Okay. So, I was at my in-laws and it was ערב פסח שחל להיות בשבת, so Shabbos was Erev Pesach. Yeah, so you did all the early things and, you know, my sisters-in-law were very worried there wasn't going to be enough bread so there was like dozens of rolls. So by the time 10:03 hit, you know, we had to get rid of it. So either you flush it down the toilet, we're not going to flush down 30
rolls down the toilet. So there's, the other option is there's a local dumpster. So my in-laws live across from an apartment complex in Queens. So we were going out there, my brother-in-law and I, and each of us had literally a bag of rolls. And this guy's getting in his car. So we're like \"what, why are we going to throw it out? We'll just give it to... we'll be nice, we'll be nice Jews.\" So we said to this guy \"do you want these rolls?\" He goes \"oh, bishvil Pesach?\" I was like \"yeah, I'm like no, sorry. These are, you can't have these.\" So, you
know, okay. Weiter. So, if you look, it's, it's hard to see this in here. I know it's hard in this, in this one. There is a Pischei Teshuva in Pischei Teshuva Sif Katan Bais that, could you have a business, could you profit from selling non-kosher wines? Meaning, could I own a wine store that profits from selling non-kosher wine? So what would you say? So the Rema would seem to say
that there are those that are lenient. There are those that are lenient. That's your parnassah, that's your parnassah. So the Pischei Teshuva in Sif Katan Bais, it's very hard to see, but the Pischei Teshuva quotes here a Levushai Srad who's melamed zechus, that they hold like the, like the Rema. It's not ideal, but you should avoid it if you could. But what are you going to do? He says מלמד זכות על מה שנוהגים עכשיו לעשות סחורה מסתמא יינם. But what are you going to do? That, they rely on it and therefore
it would be, it would be okay. Fine. That's, that's next. If the, the Rema paskens, if you go back up to this Rema, that if you accidentally bought or sold a non-kosher bottle of wine, you could benefit. The Shulchan Aruch would be machmir, but the Rema would say if you bought it by accident, you know, you know, again, you can't do things by accident every day, but it would be okay. So if you look in source 13 in the שאלות ותשובות שבט הלוי, Rav Halberstam, he quotes Rav Halberstam the following. He says לדינא שאלתי
פי הגאון רב משה הלברשטאם חבר בית דין של עדה החרדית שאלות ותשובות דברי משה והתיר לי לתת הבקבוק בסתם יינם that I could regift a bottle of wine, a bottle of non-kosher wine לאיזה נכרי מזכיר עכו״ם כדי שיעבוד יותר מהר. What does ya'avod yoser maher mean? You'll work better. Meaning, if I... I have an incentive program. Whoever gets the most sales
gets this bottle of wine. So that is done, as the Rema would say, for what reason? For benefit, for profit. So that would be okay. That would be okay to have some kind of thing where... Now, there is another issue here, that there is an issue of lo tichanem. What's the issue of lo tichanem? What's the issur? You can't give gifts to goyim. To goyim. Okay? So that's another interesting shayla which we can talk about a different time. But you could give a gift to a non-Jew if the goal for that non-Jew is to work better. That's
not considered a gift, it's considered, you know, an incentive or something. You should not send on their holiday. That's what I just mentioned, that's the Rema, I don't have it here, that's the Rema later in kuf mem hey or something. The Rema says you cannot give gifts to the goyim on their holiday. Okay, fine. If you look though in source 14, okay, if you look in source 14, it quotes the Maharam Schick. The Maharam Schick was one of the great talmidim. of the Chasam Sofer, who really took over the
mantle of leadership from the Chasam Sofer, who in the fight against the Reform movement, the Maram Shick is as fire and brimstone as the Chasam Sofer was. So the Maram Shick says, ומכל מקום יראי ה'. Fine, you're right. You have now this non-Jewish, non-kosher bottle of wine. That really, it's fine. If you don't, if it's not such a financial loss and you want to be machmir, medakdek b'mitzvos and ein hefsed,
meaning like it's not such a big deal. You know, you know, like if it's the bottle of wine that has the screw top, all right, whatever. You'll be all right. You know, you'll be all right. כי אם מעט כדאי להחוש להפסידו. To check it out. A Goy gives you a bottle of wine. All right, so it's better if you have an inexpensive bottle of non-kosher wine. Is it mutter? Probably. Is it better to drink it? Probably not. Chuck it out if you really, really don't need to. Can you regift it?
You said you could regift it. If regifting it, if it's definitely for the purpose of a benefit. If not, you're probably not for a cheap bottle of wine. Okay, source 15, says the Darchei Teshuva, sorry. Okay. Now, could I keep stam yeinam in my house? Could I keep stam yeinam in my house? There's obviously like there's obviously getting there are also times that wine could just be traif. I don't think it's not it's rare.
I don't know I don't know about wine, but you know, if you had pig fat wine, that would not be an issue of stam yeinam, that would just be an issue of kashrus. We're not there yet, we're not there yet. Okay, אם כהאי גוונא בהגהות הטור שכתב ומביא מהגהות האשירי דבכל מקום אסור לישראל להשהות יין אצלו כדי ליושנו ואפילו להסיקו. According to the Sephardim who say like the Shulchan Aruch, like the Rambam, based on how the Beis Yosef read the Rambam, that
you cannot benefit at all from this, that if you really were gifted this bottle of wine, you should not, it's assur to leave it in your house. The, yeah, b'beis Goy assur. You really, really gotta leave it out. And he writes in the middle on the line וכל זה הוא נפקא מינא לגבי ספרדים. By the way, we finally got one. Finally got one, guys. Sephardim here more machmir than us. So, win. Okay? They might use one dishwasher, but you
could keep that non-kosher bottle of wine in your basement and never drink it. וכל זה הוא נפקא מינא לגבי הספרדים שנוהגין איסור הנאה בסתם יינם because they hold it's assur. אמנם לפי שגבי מרבותינו האשכנזים אין נפקא מינא בכל הדבר ולדינא. Since we really hold like the Rambam, we would be able to keep it in the house, although the Maram Shick would say that really you shouldn't, and ideally you should chuck it away. What's the hana'ah of keeping it in the house? You can't benefit at all from it, so even though,
even though it's there, we're, we're... I would say until you give it to someone... Correct, correct, correct. Meaning according to the, to the Darchei Teshuva, I don't think it's a straight-up issur d'rabbanan, but you should really not have it because we don't hold of things. If it's assur, it's assur. If you're never going to benefit from it, what's having it in my house? So you should get rid of it. So just because it's hana'ah? Yeah, yeah, yeah. You know, there is another interesting shaila here which we're not going into too much, and that is, can you benefit from
schlepping non... like can you transport non-kosher wine? Okay? Could you, you know, I don't know, if you're an Uber driver, or you're a vendor, or the White Sox start selling wine at the games. So and you're going up and down, or the Cubs, with, you know, non-kosher wine. Okay? Could you do that? So the Shulchan Aruch would say, the Shulchan Aruch would say no, because you can't benefit from it. The Rema would seemingly say yes. There is a Shach
in se'if katan daled. So the Rema would say yes because we do allow it, and definitely in this situation it's very indirect benefit. If you look, there is a Shach in se'if katan daled, u'meitshuvas Maram mi'Lublin... nafkaminah b'din kniyah... is this right? I think so. That really you should not be providing these services. Just for clarification, beer and whiskey are not considered...
No, no, no. And why do we not put yeinam on those as well? m'de'rabbanan? Good question about that. Yeah, but if you take the other example, I'm saying m'de'rabbanan, meaning m'de'rabbanan we're taking wine and extending it to all these different levels to avoid contact... It's a great shaila, it's a good shaila. Answer, answer on shaila. Whiskey. Answer it. You know the answer. What's the answer? I don't drink wine. Meaning you're right in theory, but in order to
do that, I'd have to have a beis, meaning I can't asser things just to asser things because of, I mean, I could make a suggestion to you, you shouldn't drink beer with non-Jews, because of mishum bnosayhen. But in terms of establishing an issur, I need a precedent in halacha. You have it with wine. But the precedent is that we've asser-ed drinking with someone else. Because of wine, started with- I understand. Correct. Correct. Correct. Because at the time, people did it with
wine. Correct. No, that's how they would do avoda zara. By the way, we're going to see this, there is a chumra, most people do not hold to this chumra, that you cannot use grape juice for kiddush. Why? Why? Because you can't put grape juice on the mizbeach. Can't put grape juice on the mizbeach. So you have the- you're saying that Chazal could make an extension to say we shouldn't intermingle at all. The hope is that based on yayin, pas, and bishul,
you would make an understanding that like, I don't need Chazal every step of the way to tell me don't be an idiot, right? But in order for me to make a full-fledged issur d'rabbanan, maybe a gezeira, but for sure an issur d'rabbanan without a context of it being within the framework of a d'oreisa. Right? Meaning you have three levels of issurim. You have issur d'oreisa, you have high-level issur d'rabbanan, we'll call it divrei sofrim or mitzvos divrei sofrim. Chol HaMoed is a mitzvah divrei sofrim. It's not d'oreisa but it's d'rabbanan. Then you have a d'rabbanan. Within d'rabbanans
you have d'rabbanans and you have gezeros under those d'rabbanans. So this is not even a gezeira because, you know, ein sof. So you're right, maybe-, but bars also have peanuts. Should we not eat peanuts together? So you could make-, maybe you shouldn't. So yes, you shouldn't intermingle, but I can't establish an issur from a halachic standpoint without some context or some precedent to tell me what I'm basing this off of. And yayin, based on yayin nesech, based on stam yaynam, so there's a progression. But with the beer, there's
no progression. But your theory is 100% accurate, and I think what Chazal intended with this. Would that also apply to eating together, breaking bread? Yeah, yeah, yeah. All right, we'll hold it, we'll stop here for Ma'ariv. Next week im yirtzeh Hashem we're going to have shiur Tuesday night. Tuesday night for those that can make it. I'm not in town Monday night, so you can come Wednesday night, I just won't be here.